Wolsey, you're out!
沃尔西 给我滚出来
My Lords Norfolk and Suffolk.
诺尔福克勋爵 萨尔福克勋爵
Cardinal Wolsey.
红衣大主教 沃尔西阁下
You're dismissed as Lord Chancellor,
你已经从大法官的职位上被解职了
by the King's orders.
这是国王陛下的直接命令
You're to return to us the Great Seal.
请立即归还大法官的印玺
You'll have supper?
你是说你们在举行晚宴？
You wanted all to rule yourself, didn't you?
你就是迷恋这掌控一切的感觉 对吗
and had the lords like schoolboys, creeping in here.
然后把所有的勋爵们像小学生一样的管教 在这里苦苦挣扎是吗
Well, I am here now...
现在 我就在这
..and I will chew you up.
而且 我要生吞了你
Bones, flesh and gristle.
把你生吞活剥 骨肉分离
You're to hand over the Great Seal.
现在立刻交出大法官的印玺！
Ah!
呵
Apparently, a written request from the King is necessary.
很显然 如果你能给我一张国王陛下亲手写的辞呈也是极好的
Do you have one?
你们随身带着了吗？
No?
没有吗？
Oh, that's careless.
噢 那可真是粗心呢
My lawyer, Thomas Cromwell.
这位是我的律师 托马斯・克伦威尔
You want us to ride back to Windsor for a piece of paper?
你想让我们就为了一张纸就再骑马从这里往返温莎一次？
In this weather?
在这种恶劣的天气下？
I see, yes.
是呀是呀
Actually, my lawyer tells me I can't give you the Seal,
事实上 我的律师告诉我 我不能交出我的印玺
written request or no.
无论你们有没有国王的辞呈
He tells me that, properly speaking,
确切的说 他告诉我的是
I should hand it only to the Master of the Rolls.
我的印玺只能交还给主记事官阁下
So...
所以说呢...
you'd better come back with him.
你们回程的时候最好带着他一起来这里
I'm obliged, master.
很荣幸见到你 大法官阁下
Did you know that, or did you make it up?
你说的那些是事实 还是自己胡编的？
They'll be back in a day.
估计他们一天内就会反应过来了
Well, these days,
唉 现在这动乱的日子
24 hours feels like a victory.
能争取24个小时已经是天大的胜利了一样
Do we have refreshments for our guests?
有没有给我们的客人招待茶点呢？
Served on what? They've taken the plate.
用什么招待？连盘子都被没收了
What's this?
你穿的这是什么？
It's borrowed.
我借来的
They've confiscated my wardrobe
他们查抄了我的整个衣橱
and you know how I feel the cold.
你也知道的 我很怕冷
Thank you, Peter.
谢谢你了 彼得
This is to be Anne Boleyn's, I think.
我想这座大房子会被赏给安妮・博林吧
The King wants her to have a London residence.
国王陛下想让她在伦敦有个住所
This palace belongs to the Archdiocese of York.
这座宫殿是归约克主教区所有的
When did Lady Anne become an Archbishop?
那安妮夫人什么时候成为的大主教？
Now, now, Thomas. Everything I have, I have from the King.
别这样说 托马斯 我所拥有的这一切 都是国王陛下赏赐的
If he wants to take York Place, fully furnished,
如果他想要这座约克宫殿 那就完好无损的给他
then I'm sure we'll find some other roof to shelter under.
我们再另寻一处避身之所好了
He's expecting to find a wax figure of himself
他一直都觉得我家里有一座
with a pin stuck through it.
上面插着针的他的蜡像
Come and see me.
你跟我过来
Why, My Lord?
给我个理由 勋爵大人
When?
什么时候？
When you've mended your manners.
等你再注意一点你的礼节
What it is, to serve a prince.
你们这是在干嘛 在服侍王子吗
The gentlest, wisest prince in Christendom.
基督教世界里最宽厚最睿智的王子吗
I'll not hear a word against Henry from any man.
我以后将再也听不到任何人敢说出反对亨利国王的言语了
Do you think it's something about the English?
你觉得这一切只是英国人才会这样做吗
They cannot see a great man set up, but they have to pull him down?
他们见不得一个伟人的崛起 所以必须在他崛起前毁灭他？
It's not the English.
这不只是英国人如此
It's just people.
人性本恶
We brought the Lady Anne back from France,
我们将安妮夫人从法国
to marry into Ireland.
带回嫁到了爱尔兰
Now I hear she danced at the court masque with young Harry Percy.
现在我看到了她正在和年轻的亨利・珀西在假面舞会上尽情欢舞
Connived in dark corners with him.
在漆黑的拐角处你侬我侬
And I won't have that.
我本不应该看见的
Your grace can't think that I'm party to...
公爵大人 我真不敢想象我现在正和您在派对上...
Oh, Sir Thomas Boleyn.
噢 托马斯・博林爵士
You'd be amazed at what I can think.
你应该很惊讶我现在的想法
Anne knows things can't proceed with young Harry Percy.
安妮知道和年轻的亨利・珀西的事情不会发展顺利的
- But he believes he's free to choose his own wife.  - Free?
但亨利相信自己有权利自由的选择自己的妻子             - 自由？
Choose his own...?
选择他的...？
He's not some ploughboy!
他可不是什么随随便便的放牛娃！
He's the man who'll have to hold the north for us, some day.
他未来某一天可是我们这北方的领主啊
The Percy family comprise the noblest in the land,
珀西家族可是涵盖了这片大陆上最尊贵的贵族
whereas the Boleyns were once in...
然而博林家族嘛 却有过一次...
What? Trade, weren't you?
什么来着？交易是嘛？
Who is that?
那个人是谁？
Who's that?
是谁？
Oh, it's Stephen Gardiner, my Secretary.
噢 是斯蒂芬・伽纳德 我的秘书 [后来的温彻斯特主教]
Send him out.
让他出去
Stephen.
斯蒂芬
And who is that?
那个人又是谁？！
Never mind who that is. He's nobody.
你别管那么多了 他谁都不是
The problem is...
现在的问题是...
..my daughter and Harry Percy,
...我的女儿和亨利・珀西
I think they may have gone a little far in the matter.
我觉得他们现在有点情到深处了
It seems they've pledged themselves before witnesses...
看起来他们已经私定终身了
Well, you can forget all talk of pledges and witnesses.
这个嘛 你可以完全忽略所有的什么誓言证词
I'll get his father down from the borders
我会马上通知他的父亲从边境赶回来
and if the prodigal defies his father,
如果这个败家子竟敢忤逆他父亲的话
he'll be tossed out of his heirdom on his prodigal snout.
他会被直接剥夺爵位继承权
Now, get your daughter married into Ireland,
所以说 早点把你的女儿给嫁到爱尔兰去
before her intended hears any rumours of spoilt goods.
趁她还没听到什么风吹草动之前！
Finished, My Lord Cardinal?
说完了吗 大主教阁下？
Finished.
说完了
Butcher's boy!
狗娘养的！
Butcher's dog!
狗杂种！
Come out, dog.
过来呀 狗东西
He's talking to you.
他在和你说话
So, Master Cromwell.
所以 克伦威尔大师
William Popely tells me I might find a use for you.
威廉・波普利告诉我 你可能会对我有点用处
A man of many talents, he says.
他说 你是一个多才多艺的人
A remarkable memory?
有着惊人的记忆力?
There's a technique, My Lord.
这是有技巧学成的 勋爵阁下
I learnt it in Italy.
我是在意大利学会的
How long were you abroad?
你在国外呆了多长时间?
12 years.
12年
Where are you from?
那你来自哪里?
Putney. Left when I was a boy.
帕特尼 离开的时候我还是个小男孩
Your father?
那你父亲呢？
Blacksmith.
是个铁匠
Ah, at last!
哈 终于！
A man born in a more lowly state than myself.
一个比我出身更卑微的人！
Hey...
嘿...
- Bella!     - Eaten?
- 贝拉!      - 吃了吗?
- Mm-hmm.  - Wine?
- 吃了     - 葡萄酒?
Why not?
有何不可?
I'm going to work for him - the Cardinal.
我打算为他工作 那个红衣大主教
You know what they say in Italy?
你知道他们在意大利怎么说吗?
"II principe bisogna sceglierlo."
"王子必须做出选择"
- "You have to pick your prince."   - Doing what?
-"你必须选择你自己的王子"           - 做什么事?
Whatever he wants.
任何他想要的
We have enough.
我们有的已经足够多了
I don't want to spend my life dealing in conveyances, Liz.
我不想把我的一生浪费在买卖这些交通工具上 莉兹
Whether this man's fence should be here or here...
不管这个男人的围墙应该在这里或这里...
You know what you're doing, I suppose.
我想你应该知道你自己在做什么
At least, you always look as if you do.
至少 你总是看起来好像你知道自己在做什么
Yeah, I do, don't I?
是的 我就是这样 不是吗?
You're sweeter to look at than the Cardinal.
你看起来比那个红衣大主教要甜美的多
That's the smallest compliment a woman ever received.
这可算得上是一个女人所能收到的最差劲的恭维话了
What does our son say?
我们的儿子说了什么?
He...hopes you are well, hopes I am well,
他说...希望你一切都好 希望我一切都好
hopes his lovely little sisters Anne and Grace are well.
希望他可爱的小妹妹们安妮和格雷丝都很好
He is well.
他自己也很好
Terrible Latin.
字好丑的拉丁文
Anne's the better scholar.
安妮才是更出色的学者
Anne, go and get your breakfast.
安妮 去吃早餐吧
After I've Latin, I'd like to learn Greek.
学完拉丁语 我想学一学希腊语
Gregory has hardly any Greek.
格雷戈里几乎都不会说一句希腊话
What will London be like when that one's Lord Mayor?
要是这种人当上市长了 伦敦得变成什么样子?
From Germany.
这是德国寄来的
It came packaged as something else. I almost sent the boy away.
它被包装成其他样子 我几乎把送信的男孩赶走
- If you want to know...   - I don't want to know.
- 如果你想知道...          - 我不想知道
..it's Tyndale's New Testament, Liz.
..这是廷代尔翻译的《新约全书》 莉兹
You should read it for yourself.
你应该自己读读它
It's in English - that's the point.
它是英文翻译版 这才是重点
Not Latin.
不是拉丁文的
How can that be heresy?
基督教怎么会是误认为异教！
Read it and you'll see how you're misled.
读读它 你将发现你是如何被误导的
No mention of nuns, monks, relics...
没有提到修女 僧侣 文物...
No mention of Popes.
没有提到教皇
My prayer book's good reading for me.
我的祈祷书对我来说就很好了
Your prayer book?
你的祈祷书?
Grace, look at this.
格雷丝 看看这个
Rafe?
理夫?
Richard?
理查德?
Oh...
噢...
- Late.           - Me, or your good self?
- 你迟到了        - 我迟到了 还是你的自我感觉太良好了
- You           - he's waiting.
- 当然是你      - 他正在里面等你
The boatmen were drunk.
我的船夫们都喝醉了
I'm surprised you didn't take an oar yourself.
我真惊讶你居然自己没有带把桨
You grew up at the river, didn't you?
你在河边长大的 不是吗?
God bless you.
上帝保佑你
Thanks!
谢谢你了!
Oh, the King sent for me this morning
噢 国王今早给我来了封信
exceptionally early.
非常非常早的时候
What did he want?
他想要做什么？
Pity.
主的怜惜
A son.
和一个儿子
The King wants a son.
国王想要一个儿子
18 years of marriage, with no heir.
18年的婚姻 却一直没有子嗣继承人
He's decided some sin must have been committed, to cause this curse.
他决定有一些罪孽必须实现 来破除这个诅咒
Oh, God...
噢 上帝...
Where did you learn this?
你这是从哪学来的?
At the docks, a little after I left home.
在码头上 我离开家后不久
Earned a living from it, for a while.
有一段时间 我就靠它维持生计了
Everyone thought they could beat a child.
所有人都觉得他们怎么也不会输给一个孩子
What else should I know about you,
我还需要进一步了解
monstrous servant?
一个可怕的仆人?
Once, in Italy, I held a snake for a bet.
有一次在意大利 我拿一条蛇做赌注
Was it poisonous?
它有毒吗?
We didn't know - that was the point of the bet.
我们不知道 这个就是赌点
The sin?
罪过吗?
Oh, yes, the sin.
噢 是的 罪过
I remember when they brought the Queen over from Spain
我还记得当年他们把凯瑟琳皇后从西班牙带回来的时候
to marry Henry's brother, Prince Arthur.
把她嫁给了亨利的哥哥 亚瑟王子
16...
那年她才16岁
barely a word of English.
真的是言语难以形容
God, when she danced...
上帝 当她跳舞的时候...
...her red hair slid over her shoulder...
...她红色的头发滑过她的肩...
God forgive you?
那上帝原谅你了吗?
God forgive us all.
主会宽恕世间所有的罪恶
Then Arthur dies,
后来 亚瑟王子去世
Henry decides he'll have his brother's widow for himself.
亨利决定与自己的寡嫂结婚
Katherine declares that she's still a virgin,
凯瑟琳也坚自己仍是处子之身
poor Arthur never having touched her.
可怜的亚瑟 从未得到过她
Rome issues the dispensation
罗马方面也发出了豁免令
and any doubts anyone has...
与此同时 任何提出异议的人都...(灭口...)
But now?
可是如今呢？
Well, now, the Queen can't give the King a son.
不错  如今 王后还是不能产下王储
So, now...
所以 也就是说
..the Queen must not have been a virgin, after all.
王后当年根本不可能是处子之身
Henry says that he's lived all these years in an unlawful marriage.
亨利说这些年他都是活在不合法的婚姻关系里
Hence the sin.
全都是罪孽
So it's back to Rome, for an annulment.
所以 要请求罗马教廷 正式废除这段婚姻
She's blaming me, of course - Katherine.
当然了 凯瑟琳会十分怨恨我
She can't blame the king, so it's all my doing.
因为她自然是不能怨恨国王的 那就都由我承担吧
No matter that I've begged him not to proceed.
不论我怎么乞求他不要这么离婚 都于事无补
When she defeated the Scots, I heard she wanted to send
作战击败苏格兰的时候 我听说她想把
the Scottish King's head in a bag to Henry,
苏格兰国王的人头砍下献给亨利
to cheer him up.
以此来取悦他
Well, she's a fighter.
怎么 我觉得她是真正的巾帼英雄
Ha!
哈！
Perhaps you should teach me your three-card trick, hmm?
或许你现在应该教教我怎么玩这个捉皇后的小把戏
In case we both end up on the streets!
说不准我们哪一天也会流落街头呢！
Unpack everything. Masters, I want kindling, dry kindling.
伙计们 快把东西都卸下来  给我点引火料 快点 干的引火料
Get the fires lit. Stephen, find the kitchen.
史蒂芬 快生火 然后找找厨房在哪儿
Actually, see him in first. I need the bedding.
不 还是先照顾主教要紧 我要人给他铺床寝用具
What... Who is that? Michael? Down, off. The horses, later.
那个谁  迈克吗？ 下来  快点  等会儿再管马
We want the Cardinal in bed and warm.
我要主教大人马上能躺在暖和的床上
Come on, come on, we're not done yet!
加油 麻利点 抓紧时间
I asked if they had nutmeg or saffron
我刚才问他们有没有肉豆蔻或是藏红花
they looked at me as if I was speaking Greek.
他们都用疑惑的眼神看着我 好像我说的是希腊语
I'll have to find a local supplier.
我不得不找到当地的供货商
I shall pray for it.
我真该祈祷一下 希望自己能找到
Currently, I pray for the King and all his counsellors.
而与此同时 我却正在为国王及他的顾命大臣们祈祷
I pray for Queen Katherine and Lady Anne.
为凯瑟琳王后祈祷 和安妮夫人祈祷
I pray for Thomas More, who hates me so.
为同样深深怨恨我的托马斯・莫尔祈祷
I pray for a better harvest
为国家的风调雨顺
and that the rains might stop.
以及 人民的丰衣足食 而祈祷
I pray for everyone and everything.
我为万事万物而祈祷
It's only when I say to the Lord...
此时此刻 只有在我对上帝祷告说
"Now, about Thomas Cromwell..."
‘现在 轮到托马斯・克伦威尔...’
..does God say to me,
上帝却对我说
"Wolsey, don't you know when to give up?"
沃尔西 难道你不懂什么事适可而止吗？
Let me... Let me bless you.
来 让我代替上帝祝福你
This is what they've waited for
这是他们期盼已久的
Suffolk, Norfolk, Boleyn.
萨尔福克 诺尔福克  博林
They won't rest until they have my head.
我不死 他们是不会善罢甘休的
You should leave me, Thomas.
托马斯 你现在应该离我而去
Gardiner has.
就像伽纳德那样
Gardiner would.
卑鄙小人当然会
Tom?
汤姆
Safe journey home.
一路平安到家
I'm going to leave.
我准备走了
He says he'll send me to the Lady Anne.
他说他会送我去安妮夫人那里
I think she'll like me well enough, don't you?
我觉得她会赏识我的 对吗？
What's the point of staying here?
留在这里 还有什么意义呢
They're going to be rid of the old man.
他们都会慢慢厌倦那个老头儿的
It serves him right.
这是大势所趋
And Cromwell?
那克伦威尔呢？
The lawyer? He'll go down with him.
那个律师?  就让他和那个老头一起自生自灭去吧
Well... I say, "lawyer" -
额... 要我说 不过就是个所谓的律师而已
who knows what he is?
天知道他到底是个什么东西？
He comes from nothing.
要不是那个老头的话
The old man brings him in
他现在还只是一无所有的贱民
and in a few years, it's as if he's the one in charge...
这才不过几年光景 还真以为自己是个人物了
..as if he has some hold over the Cardinal.
以为自己接替红衣主教的权利 继续作威作福了吗
I heard he killed a man abroad and never made confession.
我听说他在国外杀了人 至今还是戴罪之身呢
But that kind...
但这种人...
they always weep when they see the hangman.
一看到刽子手 只会以泪洗面
I did, but...
是的 确实是我邀请你的 但是...
..with things the way they are with Wolsey, I thought...
只不过发生了这么多事 我以为你会陪着沃尔西的
Thomas More is here.
托马斯 莫尔也来了
Well, I expect you invited him too.
看起来你也邀请了他
- Gracia.     - Prego.
- 格雷西亚    - 普雷戈
Did you want to talk about me, Master More?
莫尔先生 你有什么想对我说的吗？
You can speak while I'm here, I have a thick skin.
趁我在这儿 你有话可以当面对我说 没事儿 我脸皮厚
No-one was talking of you.
没人想要跟你谈
Of the Cardinal, then?
那么 要说红衣主教什么呢?
Thomas, this is Monsieur Chapuys,
托马斯 这位是查普伊先生
the Emperor's new ambassador here in London.
新一任的驻英大使
Monsieur Chapuys, my friend, Thomas Cromwell.
查普伊先生 这是我的朋友 托马斯 克伦威尔
Enchanted.
很高兴认识你
I hardly know where I come from, myself.
其实我自己也不知道我是哪冒出来的
If you want to speak half-secretly,
如果您不想让我听懂你们的谈话
try Greek, Monsieur Chapuys.
那就请你们用说希腊语吧  查普伊先生
My friend, you are looking at your herring as if you hate it.
先生  如果您不待见他的话 就想象自己在看一条鲱鱼吧
- There's nothing wrong with the herring.   - Ah.
- 鲱鱼也没什么不好                          - 哈哈哈
But of Cardinal Wolsey, I'll say only this
说到红衣主教沃尔西 不得不提的是
he has brought his fall on himself.
他这辈子算是完了
He's drawn all to himself - land, money and titles.
自取灭亡罢了   土地 金钱 头衔
He's always had a greed for ruling over other men.
他总有统治众人的野心
The Cardinal's a public man.
但红衣主教到底还是个公众人物
Would you have him shrink from a public role?
你愿意帮他从这个惹眼的位置上退下来吗
Well, I think it's a little late
可是 现在为时已晚了
to read the Cardinal a lesson in humility.
就让他在那潮湿的小屋里受点教训吧
His real friends have read it long ago and been ignored.
他的好朋友们早就警告过他了 但他都置若罔闻
And you count yourself a real friend, do you?
那你觉得你是真正的朋友吗?
I'll tell him - and by the blood of Christ, Lord Chancellor,
我当然会告诉他的 以基督的名义 大法官阁下
he'll find it a consolation as he sits in exile
当他被流放的时候 他会找到自己的慰藉
and wonders why you slander him to the King.
并且疑惑为什么你会去国王那儿诽谤他
- Gentlemen... - No, let's have this straight.
- 先生们...    - 不 我们直说吧
I'm devoted to things of the spirit.
我醉心于精神世界
I care nothing for wealth.
视钱财为身外之物
So how is it I come back to London
所以这就是我回到伦敦
and find you've become Lord Chancellor?
然后发现你已经成为尊贵的大法官的原因吗?
Lord Chancellor.
尊贵的大法官
What's that?
这算什么?
A fucking accident?
是他妈的意外吗?
You're no friend to the church, Thomas.
你对教堂来说可不是个朋友 托马斯
You're a friend to one priest only
你只是一个神父的朋友而已
and he's the most corrupt in Christendom.
而且还是基督世界里最腐败的神父
You must give me the recipe for this sauce.
你一定得给我制作这个酱汁的菜谱
Thomas More is my old friend.
托马斯・莫尔是我的老朋友
You shouldn't come here to bait him.
你不该来这儿折磨他
Am I not your friend too, Bonvisi?
那我就不是你朋友吗 伯尼斯?
You know you are.
你很清楚你是的
And that's why I give you this advice.
这也是为什么我给你这个建议
The Cardinal is finished.
红衣大主教已经完蛋了
He'll go.
他迟早会离开的
And then you will be without a master to protect you.
接着你就没有主家保护你了
Leave him now.
现在就离开他
Do you think it's true?
你觉得是真的吗
The mistake was being too proud?
他犯的错是因为太自负
I remember when he used to say,
我记得他以前经常说
"The King will do such and such."
‘国王会做这些 做那些'
And then it was, "We will do such-and-such."
后来变成 ‘我们应该做这些 做那些’
Now, it's "This is what I will do."
现在变成 "这是我要做的"
No, no.
不 不
The mistake was making an enemy of Anne Boleyn.
真正的错误 是树立了一个安妮・博林这样的敌人
But then, who knew how far she'd rise?
不过呢 谁能知道她会走多远呢?
Thomas!
托马斯!
Of course, master. News from Rome.
主人 有从罗马传来的最新消息
The Emperor's troops have run wild in the city.
罗马皇帝的军队已经攻进城内了
They're killing, raping...
他们正到处杀人 强奸妇女...
Thomas More says they're roasting babies on spits.
托马斯・莫尔说他们把婴儿放在火上烤的劈啪作响
Soldiers don't have time to eat babies. They're too busy stealing.
不过士兵们根本没时间吃 他们在忙着偷东西
If the Emperor Charles had paid them once in a while...
如果查理大帝一会儿让他们吃的话
They've taken the Pope prisoner.
他们已经俘虏了教皇
What?
你说什么?
The Emperor is the Queen's nephew.
罗马皇帝是王后的侄子
If he has the Pope, then the King's divorce petition is...
如果他抓到了教皇 那国王离婚的那个请求就...
Yeah...
是啊...
In every emergency,
每次有紧急情况
look to see if there's some advantage for your prince, Thomas.
都看看是不是能给你的王子找到些什么可利用的帮助 托马斯
Ah, cherries.
啊 樱桃
How did I do that, I wonder?
我该怎么办呢 我想问
Here, take.
来，拿着
Now, in this current emergency,
但现在 在现在这个紧急情况中
it will be to me that Pope Clement looks to...
对我来说 克莱门特教皇 现在看起来就像是...
well, keep Christendom together.
好吧 是为了让所有基督国家团结在一起的 存在
So, suppose if I were to travel to France
因此 假设我到法国去
and gather together the cardinals in a council, you know,
在议会中把所有的红衣主教们叫到一起 你知道的
to conduct the business of the church in the Pope's absence?
在教皇出缺的这期间管理教堂的事务?
Now, if this business...
现在 如果教堂的事务...
happened to include the King's private matter...
碰巧包含国王的私事的话
might we not rule on it?
我们能不对它进行裁决吗?
And voila,
而且 你瞧瞧
the King of England will be a bachelor.
英格兰国王变成了单身汉
What?
什么?
Not more gossip from the silk merchants?
没从丝绸商那儿听到更多消息吗?
Rumour is the King has moved from Mary Boleyn
有流言说国王已经从玛丽・博林那儿搬出来了
to her flat-chested sister.
搬到她那个平胸的妹妹那儿去了
Anne?
安妮?
She hasn't forgiven you for that business with Harry Percy.
她还没原谅你关于哈里・珀西的事儿呢
- Well...  - Cavendish tells me she's sworn vengeance on you.
- 好吧...  - 卡文迪什跟我说 她发誓要找你报仇
Poor chit of a girl.
可怜的黄毛丫头...
The King will have her in his bed by summer.
国王在夏天会和她同床共枕
By autumn, he'll tire of her and pension her off.
到了秋天 他就厌倦她 打发她离开了
What are you doing?
你在干什么呢？
For Gregory.
为了格雷戈里
It's the same design Queen Katherine uses for the King's shirts.
这跟凯瑟琳王后给国王的衬衫是一样的设计
Well, if I were her,
好吧 如果我是她的话
I'd leave the needle in.
我肯定会在衣服上留根针的
I know you would.
我知道你会这样做的
Your sister was here today.
你妹妹今天来过了
She asked again if you'd go and see him?
她又问你能不能去看看他？
She said you'd hardly know him now. He's stopped drinking, settled down.
她说你现在已经不了解他了 他戒了酒 定居下来了
Grace, sweetheart,
格雷丝 亲爱的
will you keep away from the fire with those, eh?
你要离火炉远点
They're your angel wings.
这可是你的天使翅膀
They're just supposed to be for Christmas.
它们可是为圣诞节准备的
I know.
我知道得
All right, off you go.
好了 去玩吧
Your own father, Thomas
托马斯 你的父亲他
and he's never seen the children.
他从没见过我们的孩子们
Well, let's keep it that way.
很好啊 继续这样吧
Can I choose who I want to marry?
我能选择我想跟谁结婚吗?
What?
什么?
Within reason.
只要是合乎情理就行
Then I choose Rafe.
那我选拉夫
- You...
- 你...
Grace says I can't marry him because he's my cousin.
格雷丝说我不能嫁给他 因为他是我的表亲
Well, Richard's your cousin, not Rafe.
理查德是你的表亲 但拉夫不是
Rafe is my ward.
拉夫是我的护卫
That means Rafe's father asked me to take him in
就是说拉夫的父亲曾请求我带他入行
and bring him up in business. Do you understand?
在商业环境下把他带大 你明白了吗?
So I can choose Rafe?
所以我能选拉夫咯?
If he'll wait for you.
如果他等你的话就能
Rafe?
拉夫?
She could do worse.
她本来会选更糟的选择
- I'm too warm.     - Oh.
- 我热的睡不着      - 噢
Go back to bed, Grace, sweetheart.
回你的床上去 格雷丝 宝贝
Are you going to wear those angel wings all night?
你打算一整晚都带着那对天使翅膀睡觉吗?
Till I say my prayers.
我想祷告完再摘掉
Tell me when you're going.
跟我说你要去哪里
Liz, I'm not going.
莉兹 我哪也不去
I'm not going to France with Wolsey, remember?
沃尔西不在 我是不会去法国的 记得么?
Go back to bed, Liz.
回床上继续睡吧 莉兹
- Hello, Francis.   - Sir.
- 你好 佛朗西斯     - 先生
Anyone asks for me, I'm not here.
如果有人找我 就说我不在
Yes, Master Cromwell.
好的 克伦威尔大人
The words of the scripture are as honey to me.
圣经的语言对我来说就像蜜糖
I am drunk on the word of God.
我沉醉在上帝的话语中
I've read Tyndale's gospel.
我读过廷代尔的《新约福音》
Masses, fasting, vigils,
人群 禁食 守夜
pardons out of purgatory...
赦免于炼狱
all useless.
所有这些都是无用的
This is revealed to me.
所有的这些让我明白
For Christ's sake, man, do you think you can crawl out of your hole
上帝啊 老兄 你真以为你这德行能逃过主的圣裁吗
because Cardinal Wolsey is away?
就因为红衣大主教沃尔西阁下走了?
All that means is that Gardiner and More
这一切意味着伽纳德和莫尔
have a free hand to pursue us,
将会有更多的空闲来追捕我们
to brand us heretics.
把我们打成异教徒
Wolsey protects us.
只有沃尔西能保护我们
Wolsey?
沃尔西?
Wolsey burns bibles.
沃尔西烧了他的圣经
More will burn men.
可莫尔可是会烧死异教徒的
I met with Tyndale in Germany...
我在德国见到了廷代尔
Oh, I...
噢 我...
I don't want to know where Tyndale is.
我可不想知道廷代尔在哪
Gentlemen...
先生们...
I'm going to go to Rome and see His Holiness.
我打算去罗马 去见教皇
I know I can bring him over to our way of thinking.
我知道的 我可以让他用我们的方式来思考的
What is it?
这是怎么回事?
Say it.
快说！
She...
她...
She said she was tired this morning, after you left.
今早你离开以后她说她很累
She wouldn't eat anything, then...
她什么也不吃 然后...
she started shaking.
她就开始发抖
We called for the priest around two.
两点左右 我们叫来了牧师
She said she held a snake in Italy,
她说她在意大利抓过一条蛇
but the priest said that was just the fever talking.
但是牧师说那只是她发烧了 在说胡话
He couldn't wait to get away.
他看起来就像迫不及待要走
Did she, er...
她有没有...嗯...
Did she leave any message?
她留了什么口信吗?
For me?
有没有给我的?
Just kept saying she was thirsty.
她只是不停地说口渴
It's the girls.
姑娘们出事了
Come on, come on!
坚持住 坚持住!
Stay with me. Come on, come on, wake up, darling.
看着我 拜托 拜托 醒醒 亲爱的
Come on, come on. Can you hear me, darling?
拜托 拜托 你能听见我说话吗 亲爱的?
Can you hear me? Come on.
你能听见我吗? 拜托
Come on, please, please...
坚持住 请坚持住...
Wake up, open your eyes.
醒醒 把眼睛睁开
Open your eyes, please, darling.
快睁开眼睛 亲爱的
Please, come on...
拜托...
Come on, come on, come on, please...
快 坚持住 拜托...
Please, open your eyes, darling, come on, come on...
拜托 睁开眼睛 亲爱的 拜托 拜托...
Don't, don't.
不要 不要合上眼
- Please...come on...No...Please...
-拜托...不要...拜托...
Mercy, mercy, mercy...
让她们安然离去吧 给她们怜悯慈悲吧...
Don't.
不要这样...
It's all right.
没事的...
Go. Go now.
去吧...安心去吧...
Everybody said it was back.
人人都说它回来了
This...
这种...
..sweating sickness.
..汗热病   [亦称 流行性粟粒疹热]
I should have sent them to the country.
我应该让她们去乡下的
Liz wouldn't have let them go.
莉兹不会让她们走的
Anne cried every time you were away.
你每次离开 安妮都会哭
Did she?
是吗?
Anne did?
安妮哭过?
John and I can stay with you for a while.
约翰和我会跟你在一起待一段时间
Look after the household, until you're...
料理家务 直到你...
She wanted to learn Greek.
安妮她曾经想学希腊语
Hey...
嘿...
Oh! Ugh!
噢...呃...
Where've you been?
你去哪了?
You look like a foreigner.
你看起来就像个外国人
I am a foreigner.
我本来就是个外国人
Where'd you go?
你要去哪?
Here and there.
没有目的地 随便走走
Working for Wolsey now, I hear.
上次我听说 你现在为沃尔西卖命了
I'm a lawyer.
我是名律师
Lawyer?
律师？
You were always a talker.
你不过只是夸夸其谈而已
Slap in the mouth couldn't cure you.
耍嘴皮子功夫 是救不了你的命的
God knows you tried.
上帝知道你已经尽力了
Law?
法律？
If it wasn't for the law, I'd be a lord.
如果不是因为有法律 我早就是一名勋爵大人了
Cromwells had money.
克伦威尔有钱
We had estates.
我们有地
Thieved off us -
真是多了了你们律师
by lawyers.
把我们的地都给夺走
Suppose you don't admit to me, now, do you?
我我知道你不会承认这些的 不是吗？
Suppose you hoped I'd be dead.
估计你心里早就希望我死了千遍万遍了吧
Why are you here?
你为什么会在这儿
My wife told me I should come see you.
我妻子让我来见见你
Well, now you have.
现在你见到了
Yeah.
是
What is it?
什么事？
Master, I have a question to put to you.
主人 我想问您个问题
My father is dead and you...
我父亲去世了 现在
You are my father now.
你就是我父亲了
So, shall I change my name to yours?
所以我应该改跟着你的姓氏吗？
Your father?
你父亲？
Every day I light a candle for him.
我每天都在为他祈祷
Does that comfort you?
那你心里有好些吗？
I don't know.
说实话我不知道
Well, this...
不过...
This comforts me.
这让我释怀了许多
Richard Cromwell.
你的名字现在是 理查德・克伦威尔
Thank you.
谢谢您
- If...    - Go, go on, get out. Get out.
- 如果...  - 走 走吧 下去吧 快走
Ugh!
嗯...
Agh! Oh!
啊！
Now, get up!
快给我起来！
Get up!
起来！
Come on, boy! Let me see you stand on your feet!
来啊，小子！让我看看你有多少能耐！
- Agh!     - Get up!
- 啊！     - 给我起来！
You'll hear the King's reception of me was cool.
你应该听说了国王陛下对我的款待有多棒了
It's only partly true.
虽然说是有点夸张
Still, my mission could not be described
但我的这次任务仍不能说是
as an over-whelming success.
一个举足轻重般的胜利
The cardinals wouldn't meet me.
红衣主教们不肯见我
They said it was too hot to travel south.
说是到南方去太热了
So...what next?
所以...接下来怎么办呢？
A new plan. A Legatine Court.
一个新计划 一个宗教法庭
We ask the Pope to send his envoy to act in his name
我们要让教皇以他名义派遣特使来
and rule here in England,
治理英格兰
on the validity of the King's marriage to Katherine.
并确保国王陛下和凯瑟琳的婚姻自始至终
Hm? Huh?
嗯？哈？
Er...
呃...
When you were in France...
当你在法国的时候...
..my wife and daughters died.
我的妻子和女儿们都相继去世了
Oh, Tom...
噢 汤姆...
Whom the Lord loveth...
因主所爱...
Master Cromwell?
克伦威尔大师？
Thomas Cromwell, reading a prayer book?
托马斯・克伦威尔 竟然在看祈祷书？
Now I know how bad things are.
那么我知道事情的严重性了
How is he?
他怎么样了？
He asks after you...
你离开后...
the minute you've gone.
他马上就问起你
Worries you'll fall in the road.
担心你在路上摔下来
Have you an inventory for York Place, George?
乔治 你有约克宫殿这的财产清单吗
What?
什么？
York Place. I'll take it to her.
约克宫殿 我要送给她
To the Lady Anne?
送给安妮夫人？
Mm-hmm.
嗯哼
Well, Mark?
马克？
You're hard at study.
你在用功学习呢
How are you?
你还好吗？
It must feel strange, being back at York Place -
回到约克宫殿这让你感到陌生了吧
with the world so altered?
毕竟世界变化莫测
No.
没有
You don't miss My Lord Cardinal?
你不想念红衣大主教阁下吗？
Well, you might not think of us, Mark, but...
好吧 你可能不愿想起我们
we think of you.
但我们仍会挂念你
Pourquoi! Don't let him out!
为什么！别让我的小不点跑掉
Lady Anne.
安妮夫人
Vous etes gentil.
您可真客气
Allors...
那好
Master...
克伦威尔
Cremuel?
大人？
You have your inventories?
你把这里的清单带来了吗?
Thank you for this.
可真是多谢了你的慷慨
Since My Lord Cardinal's reduction,
自从红衣大主教阁下风光不再后
have you seen much progress in your cause?
我想您过得还不错吧？
He's the only man in England who can obtain for you what you need.
在英格兰 他是唯一能满足你所需的人
Very well.
很好
Make his case. You have five minutes.
继续为他说话  你有五分钟
Otherwise, I can see you're really busy.
如果不是的 你应该会很忙才对
The Cardinal's the only man who can deliver an annulment from the Pope.
红衣大主教是唯一有权利从教皇那里接过国王王后离婚判决的人
He's the only man who can deliver the King's conscience -
也是唯一能够拯救陛下良知
and deliver it clean.
甚至让陛下完全醒悟过来的人
If the King wants it
如果国王想要得到那份判决的话
and according to you, the Cardinal,
并且按照你所说的 红衣大主教
formerly the chief subject of the kingdom, wants it...
这位前任王国统治下的主教 也想要它
Then I must say, Master Cremuel
那我不得不说 克伦威尔大人
it's all taking a marvellous long while to come to pass.
这还真是花了很久很久的时间才得以实现啊
And she's not getting any younger.
而且凯瑟琳王后已经不再年轻了
No-one is more distressed than the Cardinal
没有人比我们的红衣大主教更紧张了吧
that the King cannot have his heart's desire,
国王得不到他内心所求的欲望
which is ever the Cardinal's desire too.
因为这同时也是红衣大主教内心的欲望
He knows that all the King's subjects
因为他知道国王所有统治下的国民
- repose their hopes in you, for an heir to the throne...  - Very nice.
- 都把他们的希望寄托在你身上 希望你能诞下王位的继承人...   - 很好
Very nice, Master Cremuel.
很好！克伦威尔大人
But try again.
有本事你再说一遍！
One thing.
有一件事！
One simple thing we asked of the Cardinal
我们要求红衣大主教做的就这么一件简单的事情而已
- and he would not.    - You know it wasn't simple.
- 但他却坚决不会去做   - 你知道那并不是简单的事
Well, perhaps I am a simple person.
好吧 也许因为我只是一个普通的人
Do you feel I am?
你觉得我是么?
You may be. I hardly know you.
也许吧 但我对你了解的并不多
You may go.
你该走了
Lady Mary.
玛丽夫人
God, I thought she would slap you.
我的天 我还以为她会狠狠扇你一耳光呢
My sister likes a good fight.
我妹妹天性比较好斗
Come again.
下次再来试试吧
I can't wait!
我已经迫不及待了!
Your sister can, I think.
我认为你姐姐能行的
Oh, she knows how to wait.
噢 她知道该如何等待的
So I hear.
据我所知
They say she and the King...
他们说她和国王...
..still haven't. It's true.
还在藕断丝连着 这是真的
She lets him pull down her shift and kiss her breasts.
她让国王为她倾倒 并亲吻她的胸脯
Good man, if he can find them.
男人一样可以 如果他能找到的话
Lady Mary, Lady Anne wants you.
玛丽夫人 安妮夫人找你
Oh, by the saints!
噢 我的天!
I need a seat in Parliament again.
我要再次申请 在议会中取得一个席位
Why?
为什么?
Because if I'm not there to speak for the Cardinal,
因为如果我不在那边为主教阁下说话
they'll kill him.
他们会马上杀了他
Cromwell, I am content you are a burgess in the Parliament.
克伦威尔 我会满足你的愿望 让你在成为议会的议员
My Lord.
谢勋爵大人
I spoke to the King for you and he is also content.
我也和国王说了 他也同意了
You will take his instructions in the Commons - and mine.
你会在下议院中接收到他和我的指令
Will they be the same, My Lord?
大人 两道指令是一样的么?
God damn it, Cromwell...
你这该死的 克伦威尔...
Why are you such a...
你为什么总是要表现成这样的...
person?
一个人呢?
It's not as if you can afford to be.
就好像你能承担的起你这么做的后果一样！
Smile away!
就这样一笑置之吧!
The King will grant you an audience,
国王会授予你一个听众席位的
but he is preparing a quarrel against you, master.
但他已经准备好和你斗法了 大师
Oh, yes!
噢 对了
He has a long memory and well remembers
他记忆力十分出色 而且记得非常清楚
when you were a burgess in the Parliament before this -
在你上一次当选议员的时候
and how you spoke against his war.
你是怎样反对他挑起的战争的
I hope he doesn't think still of invading France.
我至今仍希望他不要再想着了侵略法国
God damn you! What Englishman doesn't?
你去死吧! 有哪个英国人不这么想
We own France!
法国那地方本来就是我们所有的!
We have a right to take back our own!
我们有权去夺回属于我们自己的东西!
Mind you...
你给我听着...
You're right.
也许你说的没错
We can't win.
也许我们打不赢这场战争
But we have to fight anyway.
但无论如何我们必须要去战斗
That was what was wrong with Wolsey
这就是为什么说沃尔西犯了错
always at the treaty table.
他总是想着如何谈判签协议
How can a butcher's son understand...
一个屠夫的孩子怎么会懂...
La gloire?
拿戈卢?    [产自波尔多地区的高级红酒]
Are you a butcher's son?
你难道是屠夫的儿子吗?
Blacksmith's.
铁匠的儿子
Are you really?
你认真的?
Shoe a horse?
给马打蹄铁的那种?
If I were put to it - I was a soldier, myself.
如果我再刻苦专精一点的话 但我曾经是名战士
Were you?
是么?
Not with any English army, I'll be bound.
我敢说 你在任何的英国军队里都不够格
I knew there was something about you that I didn't like,
我知道你是有些地方很不讨我喜欢
but I couldn't put my finger on it.
但我绝对不会对你指指点点
Where were you?
说说 你当时是在哪?
Garigliano.
加里格利亚诺
With?
和谁一起?
- The French.    - Huh!
- 法国人         - 呵！
- Wrong side, lad.      - I noticed.
- 你站错队了 少年       - 我知道
Longbow-man?
那你会用长弓射箭么?
Now and then. Bit on the short side.
偶尔 但玩的不是很好
Me too.
我也是
The King can draw a bow.
国王可以拉一个满弓
Very nice.
那很厉害
Got the arm.
够得到手臂
My Lord,
勋爵大人
Esher is not suitable for My Lord Cardinal.
埃莎尔那里不适合红衣大主教阁下
He's willing to travel to his palace at Winchester.
他很愿意前往他在温彻斯特那里的宫殿
Oh, I bet he is.
噢 我打赌他肯定愿意
Nice and close to the King!
想的很美 又能很接近国王!
Don't take us for fools.
但别把我们当傻瓜
Tell your cardinal that he had his last chance, with his court,
告诉你的主教阁下 他和他所谓的法庭
here in this very building!
这是他们的最后一次机会！
Tell him to go north.
告诉他逃到北边去
He's not ready to go north.
他没有准备好去北方那边
I want him north.
我想让他去北方那边
Tell him, Norfolk wants him on the road and away from here...
告诉他 诺尔福克想让他快点上路 早早离开这里
..and tell him...
..并且告诉他...
..if he doesn't,
..如果他不愿意
I'll come to him
我会去找他
and I'll tear him with my teeth.
然后我将用我的牙齿把他撕裂
My Lord, may I substitute the word "bite" for "tear"?
大人 我能把‘撕裂’替代成‘咬’吗?
Substitute nothing, you...
没什么可替代的 你...
..you nobody.
..你这个无名小卒
For 20 years,
20年来
I have been your true wife.
我一直都陪在你身边 是你真正的爱妻
And by me, you have had many children...
我们一起生育了很多个孩子
...although it pleased God to call them from this world
...虽然上帝很宠爱他们 把他们从这个世界上带走
which was no fault of mine.
但这并不是我的过错
And when you had me first -
当你第一次拥有了我
as God is my witness, I was a true maid,
上帝为我作证 我是个真正的处子之身
without touch of man.
从没有碰过男人
And whether this is true or no,
不管你承认与否
I put to your conscience.
这答案只有你自己的良心知道
On Prince Arthur's wedding night, myself and the Earl of Oxford
在亚瑟王子的新婚之夜 我和牛津伯爵
took the prince to Queen Katherine's chambers
将王子带到了凯瑟琳王后的寝宫
and we were there when he climbed into bed beside her.
当他爬上床在她旁边时 我们都站在那里
Next morning, he comes out again, says he's thirsty
第二天早上 他再次出现 说他很口渴
and asks for some ale, because, he said...
并要一些啤酒 因为 他说
"Last night I was in Spain!"
"昨晚我身在西班牙！"
The Queen was Spanish, you see?
你们都知道 女王是西班牙人呀
It would be a poor sort of bridegroom
那是个多么可怜的新郎官啊
who'd come out in the morning and say,
谁会在大早晨就出来并且说
"Good day, masters. Nothing done!"
"多么好的一天 大师 我们什么也没做成"
He was 15, he was boasting.
他才15岁 他在吹嘘自己呀
I believe Katherine.
我宁愿相信凯瑟琳王后
Believe nobody.
不要相信任何人
You're late, Stephen. They're almost done for the day.
你迟到了 斯蒂芬 他们这一天几乎都耗光了
It doesn't matter.
无所谓
Why doesn't it matter?
为什么无所谓?
News from one of my men in Rome.
我从我的一个在罗马的手下听到了一个消息
Pope Clement is preparing to sign a treaty with the Emperor.
克莱门特教皇 正准备和罗马皇帝签署一个条约
Oh...
噢...
Your boy doesn't understand.
这男孩不懂你说的什么意思
The Emperor won't take kindly to the Pope helping
罗马皇帝是不会轻易接受教皇的帮助
to have his aunt cast off the throne.
来让她姑姑放弃王位的
I don't think your papal envoy in there
我不认为教皇的特使在那里
is likely to give the King what he wants, do you?
是想给国王他最想要的 你觉得呢?
And when he doesn't,
但如果他真的给了国王最想要的
Wolsey will be finished.
那么沃尔西就会完蛋了
And then I'll feel sorry for you.
然后我也会将为你感到十分遗憾
Except you won't.
除非你不会这样
Except I won't.
对 除非我不会这样
Cromwell? How's your fat priest?
克伦威尔? 你的那个胖牧师怎么样?
How is...?
他怎么样了...?
He cannot be well till he has Your Majesty's favour.
他不会好的 除非他得到殿下您的青睐
The list of charges against him grows every day.
指控他罪名的名单每天都在增加
Saving Your Majesty, there's an answer to each one
殿下 每个人都已经有了答案
and given a hearing, we'd make them.
给他一个听证会的机会吧 我们会成功的
Not today.
不是今天
Suffolk wants to go hunting.
萨尔福克今天想去打猎
We usually say, we gentlemen, that the hunt prepares us for war.
我们通常说 我们这些绅士们 狩猎是为将来的战争做准备
Which brings us to a sticky point, Master Cromwell.
这给我们带来很棘手的一点 克伦威尔大师
It does, indeed.
是的 确实是
You said, in Parliament, in a speech, some six years ago,
你说 在议会上 一次演讲中 大约六年前
that I could not afford a war.
说我承受不了一场战争
Wars are not affordable things.
战争是我们买不起的东西
When I went into France,
然后当我进入法国
I captured the town of Therouanne, which you called...
我围堵在了一个镇上的Therouanne 你管这叫...
- A dog-hole, Majesty.   - How could you say so?
- 一个狗洞 殿下          - 你怎么这么肯定的?
Er... I've been there.
呃...我去过那
So have I - at the head of an army!
我也是 还是统领一支军队前去
You told me I could not lead my own troops!
是你说我 不能领导我自己的军队!
You told me if I was taken prisoner,
是你告诉我 如果我被俘虏了
the ransom would bankrupt the country! So, what do you want?
赎金将使国家破产! 所以 你到底想要干什么?
You want a king to huddle indoors, like a sick girl?
你想让国王蜷缩在王宫内 像一个生病的小女孩儿?
That would be ideal, for fiscal purposes.
那样状况也许会很理想 只站在财政的角度上看
A strong man acts within that which constrains him.
一名身体强壮的男人 行动起来却会被处处受制
What constrains me?
我问你 是什么在限制我?
Distance.
是距离
When Your Majesty's ancestors fought in France,
当殿下的祖先在法国作战时
they held whole provinces.
他们攻下了一整个省
From there, they could supply, they could provision.
在那里 他们可以自给自足粮饷军备
Now we have only Calais,
可现在我们却只有加来一个城市而已
how can we support an army in the interior?
打起仗来 我们要如何才能供给一支在敌人内部的军队呢?
So next time we go into France,
所以下次我们再去法国时
we'll need a sea coast.
一定一定需要一个海岸做供给点
- Of course.Normandy, Brittany.
- 当然 比如诺曼底, 布列塔尼半岛
Master Cromwell,
克伦威尔大师
your reputation is bad.
你的名声可不是很好
You don't defend yourself?
你难道不要为自己辩护吗?
Your Majesty can form your own opinions.
殿下可以自己构成自己的观点
I can.
是 我可以
I will.
而且 我也会的
Are we to paint out the Cardinal's coat of arms?
我们现在画出穿着大衣的红衣大主教的手臂了吗?
No.
不行
Paint it again.
再涂一遍
Paint it brighter.
涂得颜色再亮点